{"tossups": [{"question": "When this man was caught in a lie about Secretary of Agriculture Clinton Anderson\u2019s findings about sugar supplies, he noted that he \u201cdidn\u2019t give a tinker\u2019s damn\u201d about what Anderson had really said. The Tydings Committee investigated this man\u2019s claim, made in a Lincoln Day speech in Wheeling, that he held a list of 205 names of State Department members with questionable loyalties. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator known for hunting communists during the Red Scare.", "answer": "Joseph<b> McCarthy</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Sopwith Camels were equipped with two of these devices, often produced by Lewis. The capture of Roland Garros\u2019 equipment helped German engineers like Anthony Fokker develop synchronization gear, permitting these closed-bolt weapons to operate through the gaps of a spinning propeller. The Browning M1919 replaced many Vickers-produced examples of, for ten points, what weapons that were mounted on World War I-era aircraft and could fire hundreds of bullets per minute?", "answer": "<b> machine gun</b> (prompt on (automatic) gun or similar general terms; accept elaborations like\u201c<b>machine gun</b>s mounted on WW1-era planes\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "That move came after the announcement of the Cohen Plan, a supposed Communist plot whose discovery allowed its President to take dictatorial power. That leader, Getulio Vargas, modernized this country\u2019s economy as part of the Estado Novo. For ten points, name this South American country whose Old Republic was dominated by an oligarchy in S\u02dcao Paulo.", "answer": "<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In a novel, Nicholas Branch is tasked with assembling information about this event, discovering the crippling dyslexia of the perpetrator. Permutations of this event are overseen by the Yellow Card Man in a 2011 Stephen King novel titled for the date of this event. This event, the subject of<em> Libra</em> and<em> 11/22/63</em>, was carried out from a school book depository in Dallas. For ten points, name this Presidential murder carried out by Lee Harvey Oswald.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> of<b> J</b>ohn Fitzgerald<b> Kennedy</b> (or<b> assassination of JFK</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2009, Karen Starko claimed that this event was exacerbated by the Surgeon General\u2019s instruction to take aspirin. Woodrow Wilson nearly died in this event, which was first reported in the United States at Camp Funston in Fort Riley, Kansas. This event, which killed about five percent of the world\u2019s population, was spread across the globe by soldiers near the end of World War I. For ten points, name this 1918 pandemic, commonly named for an Iberian country that didn\u2019t censor the high death toll.", "answer": "<b> Spanish flu</b> pandemic (accept<b> 1918 flu</b> before mentioned; prompt on H1N1 flu, flu, or influenza alone) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After helping a Senator from this party pay back improper residency expenses, Chief of Staff Nigel Wright resigned his post in 2013. Another member of this party suggested introducing a \u201cbarbaric cultural practices tip line;\u201d that politician, Kellie Leitch, is running for this party\u2019s May 2017 leadership elections. Rona Ambrose is the current interim leader of this party after the October 2015 resignation of Stephen Harper. For ten points, name this Canadian political party that was removed from power by Justin Trudeau\u2019s Liberals.", "answer": "<b> Conservative</b> Party of Canada", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A portrait of a man from this city shows him holding his chin in one hand and a teapot he is working on in another. The subject of that work created an engraving addressed to \u201cUnhappy [this city],\u201d showing 5 bleeding men on King Street, including Crispus Attucks. John Singleton Copley worked in this city when he painted Paul Revere and Samuel Adams. For ten points, name this Massachusetts city where British soldiers killed 5 American colonists in a 1770 \u201cMassacre.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Examples of this instrument include the Galician gaita and Italian zampogna, and George Buchanan claimed they were used instead of trumpets during battle starting in the mid-16th century. Contrary to legend, this musical instrument was not actually banned by the Proscription Act of 1746. The uilleann [ill-yin] variety of this instrument makes sound through drones and an unusually wide-ranging chanter and is popular in Ireland. A goatskin sac is used to store air in, for ten points, what instrument whose Great Highland variety is from Scotland?", "answer": "<b> bagpipe</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Legislation to undertake this project was introduced to Congress by Zadock Pratt. Thomas Durant helped finance this project, though scandal arose when Credit Mobilier attempted to overcharge a company for its construction. This project was completed when Leland Stanford drove in the golden spike at Promontory, linking the Union Pacific and Central Pacific lines. For ten points, name this man-made transportation route that connected the Western and Eastern United States.", "answer": "<b> Transcontinental Railroad</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During an election held in this year, Jared Ingersoll was nominated for the losing ticket\u2019s vice presidency; oddly, both main candidates ran as Democratic-Republicans in this year, including DeWitt Clinton. Fort Mackinac [mack-in-aw] was captured in this year, during which the Battle of Queenston Heights was fought and Detroit surrendered to Isaac Brock. For ten points, name this year in which James Madison was re-elected as president and in which a namesake war erupted between the U.S. and Britain.", "answer": "<b> 1812</b> (accept War of<b> 1812</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Baldus study was used to attack the injustice of this practice in the 1987 case of<em> McClesky v.</em> <em>Kemp</em>. John Stuart Mill conducted a famous debate with a Mr. Gilpin about the effectiveness of this practice in a modern society. Abolishing this practice is a requirement for joining the EU. Justice Brennan claimed that this penalty violated the Constitution\u2019s ban on cruel and unusual punishment in 1972\u2019s <em>Furman v. Georgia</em>. For ten points, name this judicial punishment whose methods include lethal injection and hanging.", "answer": "<b> capital punishment</b> (accept the<b> death penalty</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This empire was ruled by an Amorite dynasty until a sack by the Hittites and an occupation by the Kassites. This empire rivaled, then allied with, the Medians to their north. This empire was refounded after the death of the powerful Assyrian king Ashurbanipal. A law code that governed this empire contained the principle of \u201can eye for an eye,\u201d and its capital city legendarily featured intricate hanging gardens. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian empire ruled by Hammurabi.", "answer": "<b> Babylon</b>ian Empire (accept Neo-<b>Babylon</b>ian Empire after \u201crefounded\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist went to work at the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions after he was forced to step down from his position at Caltech due to his antiwar positions. This man proposed an incorrect triple helix model for DNA and recommended treating the common cold and cancer with high dosages of Vitamin C. This scientist also introduced orbital hybridization and the electronegativity scale. For ten points, name this two time Nobel laureate.", "answer": "Linus<b> Pauling</b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In one post, this man signed the Collier-Burns Highway Act to strengthen infrastructure within his state. The right for a defendant to remain silent was affirmed when the court led by this former California governor heard the case<em> Miranda v. Arizona</em>. Lyndon B. Johnson ordered this man to form a commission to investigate the assassination of John F. Kennedy. Dwight Eisenhower appointed, for ten points, what liberal Chief Justice who served from 1953 to 1969?", "answer": "Earl<b> Warren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler\u2019s forces were victorious at Kozludzha, allowing for an annexation of the Crimea in the Treaty of Kuchuk Kainarji. Disgruntled peasants attempted to overthrow this ruler in the (+) Pugachev revolt. Sham villages were allegedly constructed so that Grigory Potemkin could impress this ruler, who was brought to power in a coup against (*) </b> her husband, Peter III. For ten points, name this patron of Denis Diderot and Voltaire, an enlightened tsarina of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Catherine the Great</b> (or<b> Catherine II</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Eritrea declared independence from, for ten points, what East African country whose capital is Addis Ababa?", "answer": "Federal Democratic Republic of<b> Ethiopia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This city\u2019s downtown is nicknamed for a structure that occupies Van Buren, Wells, and Lake Streets, plus Wabash Avenue. This city\u2019s namesake river was connected to the (+) </b> <b>Des Plaines [dess plains] River in a 1900 project that reversed its flow. The second star on this city\u2019s flag commemorates an event that started at 137 DeKoven Street. This city\u2019s elevated trains form the downtown (*) </b> Loop, which is home to Willis Tower. Mrs. O\u2019Leary\u2019s cow supposedly started an 1871 fire in, for ten points, what Midwestern city, the largest in Illinois?", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>A crucial battle leading to the end of this dynasty may have been fought near Chibi City. This dynasty, which earlier fought the Xiongnu barbarians, was briefly interrupted when the</b> <b>Liu family was overthrown by Wang Mang. The Celestial Masters launched the (+)</b> <b>Five</b> <b>Pecks of Rice revolt against this dynasty in an attempt to rid the world of decadence. The Yellow Turban Rebellion brought this dynasty to an end, leading to the (*)</b> Three Kingdoms Period. Liu Bang founded, for ten points, what dynasty that shares its name with the predominant ethnicity in modern China?", "answer": "<b> Han</b> dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In this country, the U.S. distributed copies of the</b><em><b> Psychological Operations in Guerrilla </b><b>Warfare</b></em><b> manual. In 1986, the U.S. was censured by the International Court of Justice</b> <b>for mining this country\u2019s commercial (+)</b> <b>harbors. American funding to this country</b> <b>was officially halted by the Boland Amendment, but money was re-routed to one of its right-leaning factions by (*)</b> Oliver North. For ten points, name this Central American country, the subject of a scandal during the Reagan administration involving its Contra guerrillas.", "answer": "<b> Nicaragua</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s strategy of using fortified burhs is documented in the Burghal Hidage. He called together an army at Egbert\u2019s Stone in order to fight at Edington. This man forced</b> <b>the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Wedmore upon one rival following the siege of Chippenham, ensuring</b> <b>that Guthrum converted to Christianity. The Doom Book of codified laws was issued by this monarch, and the (*)</b> Anglo-Saxon Chronicle was created during his reign. For ten points, name this king of Wessex, the only English monarch to be called \u201cthe Great.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Alfred</b> the Great", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The mother of two of these people asks a favor that angers the rest of this group. Two members of this group were dubbed</b><em><b> Boanerges</b></em><b>, or \u201csons of thunder.\u201d On one occasion, a</b> <b>man estimates that this group needs at least 200 (+)</b> <b>denarii-worth of food. The treasurer</b> <b>of this group regularly stole from its funds and accompanied his teacher to the (*)</b> Garden of Gethsemane before betraying him for thirty pieces of silver. For ten points, name this group of twelve men that Jesus called to ministry in the canonical gospels.", "answer": "Twelve<b> Apostles</b> (or Twelve<b> Disciples</b> of Jesus)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One member of this group of people, Walter Jenkins, was a top aide to Lyndon</b> <b>Johnson before his arrest with another member of this group. The Mattachine Society</b> <b>promoted equal rights for these people. A member of the (+)</b> <b>San Francisco Board</b> <b>of Supervisors, Harvey Milk, became a martyr for this group, who were attacked by</b> <b>police during riots at the (*)</b> Stonewall Inn in New York. For ten points, name this group of people who gained the right to marry in<em> Obergefell v. Hodges</em>.", "answer": "<b> gay</b> and/or<b> lesbian</b> people (or<b> homosexual</b> people; accept<b> bisexual</b> people; \u201canti- prompt\u201d on LGBT or more expansive answers by saying \u201ccan you be more specific?\u201d; prompt on queer people; do not accept transgender or transsexual people)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}